<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To the Kings most Excellent Maiesty the hvmble desires of the commissioners of His Majesties kingdome of Scotland : as also the names of the said commissioners : with an order of the House of Commons testifying their loving acceptance, and thankfulnesse for their brotherly care of the publique welfare.</title>
            <author>Scotland. Parliament.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62411</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S991</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8816</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12589708</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12589708</idno>
            <idno type="VID">63855</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62411)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 63855)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 249:E134, no 4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>To the Kings most Excellent Maiesty the hvmble desires of the commissioners of His Majesties kingdome of Scotland : as also the names of the said commissioners : with an order of the House of Commons testifying their loving acceptance, and thankfulnesse for their brotherly care of the publique welfare.</title>
                  <author>Scotland. Parliament.</author>
                  <author>Lothian, William Kerr, Earl of, 1605?-1675.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament. House of Commons.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 5 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed: Earle Lothian.  Earle Lindsay.  Lord Balmerio.  Sir Thomas Morton.  Sir Thomas Hope.  Sir Archibauld Johnston Burgesses.  Sir Iohn Smith.  Master Robert Barklay.  Master Patrick Bell.</note>
                  <note>The "order of the House of Commons" is dated Jan. 17, 1641 [/42]</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Thomason Collection, British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Scotland --  History --  Charles I, 1625-1649 --  Sources.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:63855:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 112 -->
            <p>TO THE KINGS MOST EXCELLENT Majeſtie.</p>
            <p>THE HVMBLE DESIRES of the Commiſsioners of His Majeſties Kingdome of SCOTLAND: As alſo the Names of the ſaid <hi>Commiſsioners.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With an Order of the Houſe of Commons, teſtifying their loving acceptance, and thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe for their Brotherly care of the <hi>Publique welfare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>London printed, 1642.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:63855:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 113 -->
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:63855:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 113 -->
            <head>TO THE KINGS Moſt Excellent Majeſtie.</head>
            <head type="sub">The Humble Deſires of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsioners of his Majeſties Kingdom of <hi>Scotland.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>VVEe Your Majeſties humble and faithfull Subjects, Conſidering that the mutuall relation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Your Majeſties Kingdoms of <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> is ſuch, as they muſt ſtand or fall together, and the diſturbances of the one, muſt needes diſquiet and diſtemper the Peace of the other, as hath bin often acknowledged by them both: And
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:63855:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 114 -->eſpecially in the late Treatie which is ratified in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and confirmed by the publicke Faith of the Eſtates of Your Majeſties Ancient and Native King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Scotland;</hi> So that they are bound to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the Peace and Liberties of one another, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing highly concerned therein, as the aſſured meanes of the ſafety and preſervation of your owne: And finding our ſelves warranted and obliged by all meanes to labour to keepe a right underſtanding be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Your Majeſtie and Your People, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme that Brotherly affection begun betwixt the two Nations, to advance their Unitie by all ſuch waies as may tend to the glory of God, and peace of the Church, and ſtate of both Kingdomes. And like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to proffer our ſervice for removing al Ielouſies and miſtakings which may ariſe betwixt Your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie and this Kingdome, and our beſt endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours for the better eſtabliſhment of the affaires and quiet of the ſame: That both Your Majeſties Kingdomes of <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>England</hi> may be United in the enjoying of the Libetties and Peace under Your Majeſties Scepter, which is the moſt aſſured foundation of Your Majeſties Honour and Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and of the ſecurity of Your Royall Perſon. Crowne, and Dignitie: We have taken the bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to ſhew to Your Majeſtie, that we are hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily ſorry and greiv'd to behold theſe Diſtractions, which encreaſe dayly betwixt Your Majeſtie and Your People, And which wee conceive are enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd by the wicked Plots and Practiſes of Papiſts. Prelates, and their adherents, whoſe aime in all theſe Troubles, hath been not onely to prevent all
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:63855:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 114 -->further Reformation, but alſo to ſubvert the purity and truth of Religion within al Your Majeſties King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, For which end, their conſtant endeavours have beene to ſtirre up diviſion between Your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie and Your People; by their questioning the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of Parliaments, and the lawfull Liberties of the Subjects, and really weakning Your Majeſties Power and Authoritie Royall, upon pretence of defending the ſame. Whereof, by Gods Providence, being diſapointed in your Majeſties Kingdome of <hi>Scotland,</hi> they have now converted their miſchievous counſels, conſpiracies, and attempts to produce theſe diſtempers in Your Majeſties Kingdomes of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi> And therefore according to our duty to Your Majeſty, to teſtifie our brotherly affection to theſe Kingdomes and to quit our ſelves of the truſt impoſed on us. We doe make offer of our humble endeavours, for compoſing theſe differences. And to that purpoſe doe beſeech your Majeſty in theſe extremities, to have recourſe to the ſound and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full advice of the Honourable Houſes of Parliament. And to repoſe thereupon, as the onely aſſured and happy meanes to eſtabliſh the proſperity and quiet of this Kingdome. And in the depth of your Royall Wiſedome to conſider and prevent theſe apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of feare, which may poſſeſſe the hearts of Your Majeſties Subjects in your other Kingdomes, if they ſhall conceive the authority of Parliaments, and the Rights and liberties of the Subject to be here called in queſtion; And we are confident, if Your Majeſty ſhall be graciouſly pleaſed to take in good part, and give care to theſe our faithfull and humble deſires,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:63855:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 115 -->that the ſucceſs of Your Maieſties affaires, howſoever now perplexed, ſhall be happy to Your Majeſty, and joyfull to all your people: over whom that Your Majeſty may long and proſperouſly raigne, is the conſtant and fervent prayer of us</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Maieſties faithfull Subiects and Servants.
<list>
                     <item>Earle <hi>Lothian.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Earle <hi>Lindeſay.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Lord <hi>Balmerino.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Sir <hi>Thomas Morton.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Sir <hi>Thomas Hope.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Sir <hi>Archibauld Johnſton</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Burgeſſes.
  <list>
                           <item>Sir <hi>Iohn Smith.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Maſter <hi>Robert Barklay.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Maſter <hi>Patrick Bell.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="order_to_thank">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:63855:4"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 115 -->
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Die Lunae <hi>17.</hi> Ianuar. <hi>1641.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>THe Houſe of Commons having conſidered, both that paper given in to them from the Scottiſh Commiſſioners upon Saturday laſt, as like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe their advice lately given to his Majeſtie, by occaſion of theſe preſent troubles, which at the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treaty of the ſaid houſe, they have communicated to them, and finding therein a large teſtimony of fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity to the King, of affection to the State, and of wiſedome for the honour, ſecurity, and peace of his Majeſty, and both Kingdomes, doth hereby declare that they have herein done that which is not onely very acceptable to this Houſe, but likewiſe that which is of great advantage to both Nations. And therefore have ordered, that Sir <hi>Philip Stapleton,</hi> M. <hi>Hampden,</hi> M. <hi>Fynes,</hi> M. <hi>Pym,</hi> M. <hi>Arthur Goodwin,</hi> Mr. <hi>Long,</hi> Sir <hi>Henry Vane,</hi> Iunior; or any three of them ſhall returne them very hearty and affectionate thanks in in the name of this Houſe. And this Houſe doth fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deſire them that according to their affections already expreſſed, they will continue their care and endeavours to remoue the preſent diſtractions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, as alſo to preſerve and confirme the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on betweene the two nations ſo happily begun.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Hen. Elſing Cler. D. Com.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
